in this problem
we must ask the user if they want the
program to print something
if the user enters y the program will
print the string
something otherwise nothing will be
printed
the first step of this problem is just
to prompt the user
[Music]
so based off of the problem description
we know we want to ask the user
do you want me to print something
[Music]
and in parentheses we'll display y or
n this is telling the user what we want
them to enter
now we want to save the user input into
a local variable so that we can use it
later in our program
to check its value
so let's call this local variable choice
and we'll use the get s method to get
this user input
to be stored in choice
let's just run our program as it is
before we continue coding more of our
solution
[Music]
so the program prompts us do you want me
to print something
and at this point we haven't specified
any action to take so
no matter what we input the program
won't print anything
but our prompt is working correctly so
we can move forward
we know we want to print the string
something
if the user input is y
so let's compare choice to y
[Music]
and if choice is equal to y then we'll
output
the string something
if choice is not equal to y then we
don't need to print anything
so let's run our program again
and when prompted this time we'll input
y
and we expect that the program will
output something
[Music]
and you can see that it doesn't
so we need to think about why that is
[Music]
we can comment out our if statement
right now and let's just
print choice to the screen and see what
exactly that value is
now you'll notice that i'm using p p
calls
inspect on its argument
[Music]
so when we input y
you can see there's a newline character
at the end of our user input
so we input y but then we had to hit the
enter
or return key to get the program to
recognize our user input
and that's why we have a new line
character at the end of this input
so our choice variable is actually not
equal to
the string y because we also have a new
line character at the end
[Music]
that's why on line four when we compared
choice to the string y
it returned false
so how can we remove this newline
character
we can do that by calling chomp on the
user input
so we'll use get s to get the user input
and then call chomp on it when we store
it into our choice local variable
so let's run our program one more time
printing the value of choice on line
three again
and we'll input the same lowercase y
and hit enter and now you can see that
there is no newline character at the end
of our user input
we removed it when we sort it into the
choicelocal variable
using chomp
[Music]
so now let's uncomment our if statement
and see if we can get our program
working as we intended
running the program will enter y and
this time we'll
expect that the program will output
something
[Music]
and it does so that's great let's run
our program again
and input something other than y
[Music]
nothing is printed now you'll see that
our prompt seems to indicate that the
program will only accept a y
or an n but we haven't actually
implemented that functionality in this
solution
so our program should run no matter what
the input is
but only output something if we input y
[Music]
and that's the behavior that we're
seeing
now you'll notice in our code that we
only check if choice is equal to a
lowercase y
so what do you think would happen if we
input an uppercase y
[Music]
our program will not output something
and that's because
our comparison doesn't include the upper
case y
typically when you're asking for user
input you will want it to be case
insensitive
so if you're asking the user to input
yes or no you would want to recognize
that yes or no
whether the user input it with uppercase
letters or
lowercase characters so one way we could
handle this
is to use the logical or operator
if choice is equal to a lowercase
y or if choice is equal to an uppercase
y
then output something
and this will work just fine
you can see now our uppercase y is
recognized in the same manner as when we
input a lowercase y
[Music]
so in that way our program is now case
insensitive
another way that we could handle this is
to call the string
down case method on our input when it's
received
and again i'll just comment out this if
statement for a moment so we can see
what our input looks like now
[Music]
if i run the program and input an
uppercase
y
now the program prints the choicelocal
variable back to
me and you can see that it's lowercase
so one way to make your user input case
insensitive
is to call down case on that input when
you store it into a local variable
and then in the rest of your program as
you are comparing or manipulating this
value
you're always working with a lowercase
letter
so now that we've made that change let's
just run the program one more time
to see it in action
[Music]
and you can see our program will still
work as expected
you